Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.14
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Campaign for U.S. Senate, 1991; XIV.
  - Issue Research, 8.
    - Research on Pennsylvania Issues, including Thornburgh's Gubernatorial Record
      - "An Analysis of the Jobs-At-Risk Associated with Mandated Employer Health Insurance," report by the Partnership on Health Care and Employment, November, 1991 (Box 942, Folder 2)
      - Health insurance, medical care and health policy, 1987-1991 (Box 942, Folder 3-5)
      - Senator John Heinz statements on health care, 1986-1991 (Box 942, Folder 6)
      - Pennsylvania state tuition increases, 1991 (Box 942, Folder 7)
      - Pennsylvania budget and taxes, 1991-1992 (Box 942, Folder 8)
      - Tax increases in other states, August 29, 1991 (Box 942, Folder 9)
      - State unemployment rates, 1986-1991 (Box 942, Folder 10)
      - Pennsylvania tax reform legislation, 1991 (Box 942, Folder 11)
      - Crime and the Pennsylvania criminal justice system, 1973 (Box 942, Folder 12)
    - Federal Issues, including Thornburgh's Attorney General Record
      - Public relations policies and "leaks" at the U.S. Department of Justice (DOJ), 1989 (Box 942, Folder 13)
      - Background on the specialty steel industry in the United States, undated (Box 942, Folder 14)
      - Thornburgh's finances "flap", 1988-1991 (Box 942, Folder 15)
      - Supplemental Security Income (SSI) modernization project, July 31, 1991 (Box 942, Folder 16)
      - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), 1991 (Box 942, Folder 17)
      - Fire and emergency services, 1991 (Box 942, Folder 18)
      - Medicare physician reimbursement, August 3, 1991 (Box 942, Folder 19)
      - Questions and answers for Attorney General Thornburgh regarding his record at the Department of Justice (DOJ), July 19, 1991 (Box 942, Folder 20)
      - American Civil Liberties Union, "flap", October, 1988 (Box 942, Folder 21)
      - Bank of Credit Commerce International (BCCI) investigation, 1988-1991 (Box 943, Folder 1)
      - Bank of Credit Commerce International (BCCI) investigation, links to Senate Democrats, July, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 2)
      - Civil justice reform, August-September, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 3)
      - Americans with Disabilities Act (ADA), March, 1990-May, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 4)
      - Comprehensive American Health Care Act of U.S. Senate (S.B. 454), February, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 5)
      - AIDS, 1988-1991 (Box 943, Folder 6)
      - National debt, September 28, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 7)
      - U.S. economy, 1986 (Box 943, Folder 8)
      - Emergency Economic Growth and Job Creation Act, July-September, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 9)
      - Positions on family and medical leave, September-October, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 10)
      - Federal export programs, September, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 11)
      - House Majority Leader Richard Gephardt's views on the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), May-October, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 12)
      - Attorney General's responsibilities in the Department of Justice (DOJ), 1989-1991 (Box 943, Folder 13)
      - Attorney General Thornburgh's resignation letter to President Bush, August 9, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 14)
      - Thornburgh's adoption program for the Department of Justice (DOJ), October 5, 1989 (Box 943, Folder 15)
      - Activities of the Antitrust Division, August 27, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 16)
      - Asset forfeiture criticisms and talking points, August 27, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 17)
      - Asylum regulations, July 18, 1990 (Box 943, Folder 18)
      - President Bush's remarks to the Fraternal Order of Police, August 14, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 19)
      - Office of the Attorney General (OAG) redecorating "flap", August 1, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 20)
      - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) request regarding furnishing of the Office of the Attorney General (OAG), October 3, 1990 (Box 943, Folder 21)
      - Exxon Valdez oil spill, July 22, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 22)
      - "The Growing International Role of the Justice Department," article by Attorney General Thornburgh, World Affairs Journal: A Compendium, Vol. 1, No. 1, April 24, 1989 (Box 943, Folder 23)
      - Remarks of Attorney General Thornburgh at his Farewell Ceremony, August 15, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 24)
      - Favorable quotes and articles regarding Thornburgh's record as Attorney General, August 1, 1991 (Box 943, Folder 25)
      - Thornburgh's achievements as Attorney General, 1988-1991 (Box 943, Folder 26)
      - Thornburgh's speeches as Attorney General (selected), 1988-1991 (Box 943, Folder 27)
      - News releases regarding Thornburgh as Attorney General (selected), 1988-1991 (Box 943, Folder 28)
      - Thornburgh's record as Attorney General, 1988-1991 (Box 943, Folder 29)
      - Don Bailey, Auditor General, and Hubco Ford Truck Sales "flap", 1987-1988 (Box 944, Folder 1)
      - Attorney General Nomination Hearings before the Senate Judiciary Committee, August 5, 1988 (Box 944, Folder 2)
      - Domestic Policy Council (DPC) status reports and policy initiatives, 1990-1991 (Box 944, Folder 3)
      - Inslaw case, 1990-1991 (Box 944, Folder 4)
      - Irish Republican Army (IRA), Joseph Doherty political asylum and deportation, 1989-1991 (Box 944, Folder 5)
      - Organized Crime Strike Forces, April, 1989 (Box 944, Folder 6)
      - Pornography, child exploitation and obscenity, 1989-1991 (Box 944, Folder 7)
      - Thornburgh Recusals, February, 1989-June, 1990 (Box 944, Folder 8)
      - Savings and Loan scandal accomplishments, July-October, 1991 (Box 944, Folder 9)
      - Bank of Credit Commerce International (BCCI) and Savings and Loan, 1988-1991 (Box 944, Folder 10)
      - Sentencing Commission guidelines, October, 1990-August, 1991 (Box 944, Folder 11)
      - "Stonewall Congress", 1990-1991 (Box 944, Folder 12)
      - Thornburgh and airplane travel "flap", August-September, 1991 (Box 944, Folder 13)
      - Drug allegations regarding son of the Attorney General, August, 1990 (Box 944, Folder 14)
      - "Weed and Seed" reform to prevent illegal drug use and drug trafficking, August-October, 1991 (Box 944, Folder 15)
      - Wichita, KS case, August-September, 1991 (Box 944, Folder 16)
      - Worklife Policy, May 17, 1991 (Box 944, Folder 17)
      - U.S. Congress ethics related issues, 1991 (Box 944, Folder 18)
      - Positions of Senator John Heinz on issues, including legislation sponsored by him, 1981-1991 (Box 944, Folder 19)
      - National Governors' Association (NGA) recommendations on Social Security, 1981-1987 (Box 944, Folder 20)
      - Tony Grosso, 1978-1991 (Box 944, Folder 21)
    - Campaign Issues Background
      - Past positions on issues, 1970-1991 (Box 945, Folder 1)
      - Positions on issues, with overview, July 15, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 2)
      - Federal budget cuts, August 5, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 3)
      - Tax cuts proposal, September 28, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 4)
      - Wetlands policy, September-October, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 5)
      - Environment, September, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 6)
      - Clarence Thomas, October 15, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 7)
      - Pornography, September, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 8)
      - Striker replacement, September-October, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 9)
      - Bank of Credit Commerce International (BCCI), crime, civil rights, and former Deputy Attorney General Donald Ayer, September-October, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 10)
      - Israel, September 23, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 11)
      - Philadelphians for Good Government (PGG) poll, October 28, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 12)
      - Political reports and publications (includes Pennsylvania Report), June-September, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 13)
    - Research on Governor Robert Casey and his Gubernatorial Record
      - 1990-1991 Budget (Box 945, Folder 14)
      - Tax portions of the 1991-1992 Budget (Box 945, Folder 15)
      - Casey's "negative" initiatives, July 15, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 16)
      - Attacks on Thornburgh, September 6, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 17)
      - Worker's Compensation program, March-June, 1987 (Box 945, Folder 18)
      - Cabinet appointments, 1987 (Box 945, Folder 19)
      - Ben Franklin Partnership cuts, April-August, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 20)
      - Health Care Task Force, undated (Box 945, Folder 21)
      - Environment programs, July 6, 1990 (Box 945, Folder 22)
      - Economic development, 1987-1989 (Box 945, Folder 23)
      - William Keisling, chief of staff, bond counsel, 1987-1989 (Box 945, Folder 24)
      - Unemployment Compensation fund, 1988-1991 (Box 945, Folder 25)
      - Proposals and initiatives, in campaign and early in gubernatorial term, 1986-1987 (Box 945, Folder 26)
      - Newspaper clippings regarding Casey's 1986 campaign, election and victory, May-December, 1986 (Box 945, Folder 27)
    - Harold Miller Campaign Files
      - Assistance for Workers Under the Trade Act of 1974, undated (Box 945, Folder 28)
      - Miscellaneous research on Wofford and Thornburgh positions and general campaign information, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 29)
      - Information on Arlen Specter and Carl Feldbaum, July-September, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 30)
      - Katie True, of Pennsylvania's AWARE program, request for Harold Miller to visit Lancaster County, August 26, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 31)
      - Federal Election Commission's complaints against the Thornburgh campaign, October 8, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 32)
      - Harold Miller's meeting with Bob Benko, regarding Pennsylvania statistics, July 22, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 33)
      - Status of projects in the Policy Development Office in Pennsylvania, July 17, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 34)
      - Senator John Heinz legacy, undated (Box 945, Folder 35)
      - PennDOT maintenance workers furlough issue, September-October, 1991 (Box 945, Folder 36)
      - Americans for Tax Reform pledge, September 17, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 1)
      - Thornburgh at Kirkpatrick and Lockhart (K&L), September 5, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 2)
      - Robert Kennedy (Attorney General) makes bid for Senate seat, 1964 (Box 946, Folder 3)
      - Legislative agenda at the U.S. Senate, May 10, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 4)
      - 112th Air National Guard Unit, September-October, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 5)
      - Matries Coal Company mine loan, September, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 6)
      - Trade bill, 1989-1991 (Box 946, Folder 7)
      - Capital gains, 1989-1991 (Box 946, Folder 8)
      - Striker replacement, July-September, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 9)
      - "Border adjustable" taxes, September 4, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 10)
      - President Bush's tax proposal, October 8, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 11)
      - Possible tax initiative, August 30, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 12)
      - Working Family Tax Relief Act, September 9, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 13)
      - Tax relief to families with working children, July 27, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 14)
      - Expiring tax credits, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 15)
      - Earned Income Tax Credit (EITC), 1990-1991 (Box 946, Folder 16)
      - Senator Lloyd Bentsen tax cut proposal, October 25, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 17)
      - Thornburgh accomplishments in international trade, 1983-1986 (Box 946, Folder 18)
      - Problems with the Shared Ride program, March 20, 1986 (Box 946, Folder 19)
      - Congressional ethics, 1989-1991 (Box 946, Folder 20)
      - State Workmen's Insurance Fund (SWIF), February 1, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 21)
      - Tax increases, New Jersey v. Pennsylvania, August 19, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 22)
      - International League of Human Rights, May 15, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 23)
      - Edmund Reggie indictment (Savings and Loan), August 30-September 14, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 24)
      - Pennsylvania Statewide survey by Millersville University, Center for Politics and Public Affairs, October 29, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 25)
      - World federalism, August 29, 1991 (Box 946, Folder 26)
    - Campaign Controversies
      - Thornburgh administration phone bill "flap", May-July, 1986 (Box 946, Folder 27)
      - Jack Nard "flap", 1967-1988 (Box 946, Folder 28)
      - Governor's Mansion usage "flap", January, 1983 (Box 946, Folder 29)
      - Transportation and security for Thornburgh's sons "flap", 1984-1986 (Box 946, Folder 30)
      - Cheese "flap" and food surpluses, 1983-1986 (Box 946, Folder 31)
      - Capitol addition "flap", 1986-1987 (Box 946, Folder 32)
      - Bond counsel and lawyers "flap", 1984-1988 (Box 946, Folder 33)
    - Clippings regarding the Senate Race and Various Issues
      - 1978-1991 (Box 946, Folder 34-36)
  - Oppositions Research, Harris Wofford, 9.
    Thornburgh's opponent, Senator Harris Wofford, previously had served under Pennsylvania Governor Robert Casey as Secretary of Labor and Industry (L & I) from 1987-1991. Then, after U.S. Senator John Heinz (PA) died in May 1991, Governor Casey appointed Wofford to fill Heinz' seat, until a special election could be held to elect a new Pennsylvania Senator. Wofford had also been an aide in the Kennedy administration and was the former president of Pennsylvania's Bryn Mawr College. Thornburgh was not impressed with Governor Casey's choice of the 65-year-old Secretary as U.S. Senate candidate, saying, "I knew Wofford slightly and regarded him as a classic 1960s liberal; he had a distinguished record in the civil rights area but was hardly a powerhouse candidate for the 1990s. Media reaction to the appointment was similar" (Evidence, p.300).
    Harold Miller, the primary researcher for the campaign, was responsible for providing information and research about Wofford, his record as president of Bryn Mawr, as secretary in the Casey Administration and as interim U.S. Senator. Harold Miller's other issue research will be found in the "Issue research" materials in this campaign.
    The Opposition research materials are organized as follows: 1) Wofford's record, research on his life in public service, as president of Bryn Mawr College, Pennsylvania Labor and Industry Secretary, and U.S. Senator; 2) Wofford's positions on issues, as used in his campaign; 3) "The Campaign," core group of Wofford campaign planning materials, including finances, advertisements, debates, and endorsements; 4) Clippings, from Wofford's years under Governor Casey up and including this election.
    - Research on Wofford's Record
      - Pre-gubernatorial Record: President of Bryn Mawr College and Kennedy Administration
        - Bryn Mawr College: budgets and deficits, 1970-1977 (Box 947, Folder 1)
        - Bryn Mawr College, budgets for the President's office, 1972-1974 (Box 947, Folder 2)
        - Bryn Mawr College, General fund, gifts and unrestricted resources, 1955-1974 (Box 947, Folder 3)
        - Bryn Mawr College, financing, investments and endowments, 1970-1976 (Box 947, Folder 4)
        - Bryn Mawr College, Treasurer's Preliminary Report on Operations, 1971-1976 (Box 947, Folder 5)
        - Bryn Mawr College and other community college tuition rates, 1969-1977 (Box 947, Folder 6)
        - Solicitation of funds from Adnan Khashoggi, prominent international arms dealer and orchestrator of the Iranian arms scandal, 1970-1978 (Box 947, Folder 7)
        - Lemann, Nicholas, "The Unfinished War," The Atlantic, Wofford's record with the Kennedy administration, December, 1988 (Box 947, Folder 8)
      - Record as Pennsylvania Secretary of Labor and Industry under Governor Robert Casey
        - Secretary Wofford's testimony before the Pennsylvania State Senate Committee of Appropriations, budget hearings for the Department of Labor and Industry, 1987-1991 (Box 947, Folder 9)
        - Labor record, 1987-1991 (Box 947, Folder 10)
        - Illegal use of federal funds to send Casey Administration public relations letter to 235,000 employers in Pennsylvania, March-May, 1990 (Box 947, Folder 11)
        - PennSERVE program for job training and community service, 1989-1991 (Box 947, Folder 12)
        - Resignation letter to serve as U.S. Senator after the death of Senator John Heinz, May 8, 1991 (Box 947, Folder 13)
      - Record as Appointive U.S. Senator and Related Materials
        - Governor Casey's announcement speech that Wofford replace Senator John Heinz in the U.S. Senate, May 8, 1991 (Box 947, Folder 14)
        - Remarks made on the floor of the U.S. Senate, May 9-October 8, 1991 (Box 947, Folder 15)
        - Voting record in the U.S. Senate, July-October, 1991 (Box 947, Folder 16)
        - Vote on Department of Transportation appropriations that cost Pennsylvania 14 million dollars in federal highway funds, September 18, 1991 (Box 947, Folder 17)
        - Sponsored and co-sponsored bills, May-October, 1991 (Box 947, Folder 18)
        - "Waste Watch" rating in the Senate, by the Council for Citizens Against Government Waste (CCAGW), 1991 (Box 947, Folder 19)
        - Wofford making commitments of position on National Energy Security Act in return for efforts to secure funds for campaign, November 1, 1991 (Box 947, Folder 20)
        - Allegheny Busway Project campaign fraud, September 12, 1991 (Box 947, Folder 21)
        - Memorandum regarding Wofford and Peace Corps, August 29, 1991 (Box 947, Folder 22)
        - "Spare Us from Harris: Senator Harris Llewellyn Wofford Fact Book," prepared by the Republican State Committee of Pennsylvania, September-October, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 1)
        - Negative facts about Wofford's record, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 2)
    - Campaign Positions
      - Abortion, July 18, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 3)
      - Agriculture, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 4)
      - Capital gain tax cuts, September 20, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 5)
      - Civil disobedience: Wofford's remarks to the American Bar Association (ABA), August 6, 1968 (Box 948, Folder 6)
      - Civil Rights Bill, October 29, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 7)
      - Drug kingpins, June-October, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 8)
      - Environment, October 23, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 9)
      - Environment Crimes Bill, October 10, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 10)
      - Gun control, May 25, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 11)
      - Higher education, September-October, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 12)
      - Israel, June 17, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 13)
      - Military base closings, September 11, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 14)
      - Miscellaneous positions, August-September, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 15)
      - National health insurance, October 31, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 16)
      - North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA) and "fast track", September, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 17)
      - Nuclear arms race and California Democrat Alan Cranston, 1983 (Box 948, Folder 18)
      - Pornography, September 20, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 19)
      - Product Liability Reform Act, October 29, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 20)
      - Striker replacements, August-September, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 21)
      - Union County, PA and hazardous waste, November 1, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 22)
      - Women, 1968-1991 (Box 948, Folder 23)
    - The Campaign" (Wofford)
      - Democratic Party platform, 1980-1984 (Box 948, Folder 24)
      - Hiring James Carville as campaign consultant, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 25)
      - Campaign staff, July 29, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 26)
      - Poll conducted by Petts Research, Inc., August-September, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 27)
      - Campaign contributions, October 22, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 28)
      - Fundraising events, September 16, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 29)
      - Finances and income, June-September, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 30)
      - Campaign funds and receipts, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 31)
      - Citizens for Senator Wofford memoranda, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 32)
      - Books and articles by and about Wofford, 1946-1991 (Box 948, Folder 33)
      - Attacks on Thornburgh: "burning records" "flap", 1987 (Box 948, Folder 34)
      - Attacks on Thornburgh, false advertising, September 3, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 35)
      - Attacks on Thornburgh, negative advertising and campaign bulletins, October-November, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 36)
      - Attacks on Thornburgh, involvement in the Bank of Credit Commerce International (BCCI) scandal, 1988-1991 (Box 948, Folder 37)
      - Pro-Wofford advertisements, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 38)
      - Anti-Wofford advertisements, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 39)
      - Debate between Thornburgh and Senator Wofford, October 18, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 40)
      - Endorsements for Senator Wofford, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 41)
    - News Clippings regarding Campaign and Election
      - May-December, 1991 (Box 948, Folder 42-44)
  - News Clippings, 10.
    The news clippings here are extensive, despite the short period of the campaign, August 1991-November 1991. Here the researcher will find articles from several newsgathering sources making up three sections: daily clippings about the election including prospectively (April 1991-November), Republican Rumbles (April 1991-March 1992), and AM/PM clippings (from the Department of Justice, August-November). While the time period is brief, these articles will provide researchers with complete documentation of the daily ups and downs and issues of the campaign. All three sections are arranged chronologically.
    - Daily Clippings, April-October 28, 1991 (Box 949, Folder 1-9)
    - Daily Clippings, October 29-November, 1991 (Box 950, Folder 1-2)
    - Campaign Cartoons, Fall, 1991 (Box 950, Folder 3)
    - Daily Clippings, undated (Box 950, Folder 4)
    - Republican Rumbles, April-May, 1991 (Box 950, Folder 5-6)
    - Republican Rumbles, June-September, 1991 (Box 951, Folder 1-5)
    - Republican Rumbles, October-December, 1991 (Box 952, Folder 1-3)
    - Republican Rumbles, January-March, 1992 (Box 953, Folder 1-3)
    - DOJ: AM/PM's, August-November, 1991 (Box 954, Folder 1-4)
  - Ephemera, 11.
    The files contain all the typical campaign ephemera, including buttons, fliers, bumper stickers and brochures.
    - Memorabilia, ephemera and Thornburgh stationery, 1991 (Box 955, Folder 1)
    - Buttons, brochures, handouts and bumper stickers, 1991 (Box 955, Folder 2)
  - Kirkpatrick and Lockhart (K & L), 12.
    After Thornburgh resigned as Attorney General to run for the U.S. Senate seat, he rejoined Kirkpatrick & Lockhart, as he had done in the past when not holding public service positions. Thus the files contain some campaign related materials, from August-November 1991, but also event, trip and correspondence files from following the election. Of note is the fact that having lost the election, Thornburgh naturally was expecting to remain with the law firm. However, as with his career in the past, he was not expecting the call which came from President Bush, on February 3, 1992, stating "I'm not sure if this is something you would be interested in, but we need some help at the United Nations" (Evidence, p. 316).
    The files are primarily correspondence, event, and schedule related. They include both the campaign, and the post election period, prior to Thornburgh's subsequent naming as Under-Secretary-General of the United Nations, in February.
    Of note are the files from the Rome Vatican-sponsored conference on drug and alcohol abuse. Experts from around the world attended and the trip gave Ginny Thornburgh the opportunity to start developing the agenda for the November 1992 disability conference. Also of particular interest are the files from Thornburgh's debate before the distinguished Oxford Union Society, entitled "This House Believes that British Citizens Need a Bill of Rights."
    - Correspondence
      - Pre-election congratulatory correspondence from miscellaneous persons, April-September, 1991 (Box 956, Folder 1-6)
      - Pre-election congratulatory correspondence from ambassadors and foreign dignitaries, May-September, 1991 (Box 956, Folder 7)
      - Pre-election congratulatory correspondence from US Attorneys, August, 1991 (Box 956, Folder 8)
      - Pre-election congratulatory correspondence from Washington DC persons, August, 1991 (Box 956, Folder 9)